Guide to the Max Shachtman Papers TAM.103
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
- Series II: Research Notes for "The History of the Communist International" (not microfilmed)
  - PART B: "THE HISTORY OF THE COMMMST INTERMATIONAL" BY TOPIC
    - Ruth Fischer (articles and photos) - A. Maslow; clipping on H. Eisler, 1920s-1950s (Box 23, Folder 9)
    - "Freemasonry", 1900-1914, 1944 (Box 23, Folder 10)
    - East German Jews, 1923 (Box 23, Folder 11)
    - '"Meories of Imperialism and War", 1914-1916 (Box 23, Folder 12)
    - Inprecor - Italian Fascism, "Weakest Link" Theory, Comintern and Pussian Rev., 1900-1930s (Box 23, Folder 13)
    - Independent Party, undated (Box 23, Folder 14)
    - Intellectuals, 1900s-1930s (Box 23, Folder 15)
    - "Kamenev's Last Essay" by Chimen Abransky, undated (Box 23, Folder 16)
    - Kautsky, Karl - writings, 1900s (Box 23, Folder 17)
    - Lenin on Barbarism vs. Barbarism, 1918 (Box 23, Folder 18)
    - Lenin on "Opportunism", Labor Aristocracy, 1907-1961 (Box 23, Folder 19)
    - Lenin School - Comintern Schools, 1920s-1930s (Box 23, Folder 20)
    - "Leninism", Pre1917 (Box 23, Folder 21)
    - Lenin's struggle in the Int'l (excerpts from various sources), 1900s-1930s (Box 23, Folder 22)
    - Marx and Foreign Policy, 1860 (Box 23, Folder 23)
    - Marx and Engels letters (Labour Monthly reprints) - Lenin documents, Marx + Engels on Ireland and the British Working Class Movement III, 1879-1895 (Box 23, Folder 24)
    - National question - Self-determination, "Red Imperialism", 1919-1923 (Box 23, Folder 25)
    - Nationalization - Lenin on workers control, Nationalization mania, 1917-1919 (Box 23, Folder 26)
    - Party Historiography - Documents and -Bibliography, undated (Box 23, Folder 27)
    - Peasants - Holland, Eastern Europe, France, 1920-1925 (Box 23, Folder 28)
    - Personalities: Lenin, Trotsky, Mussolini, Radek, etc., 1900s-1930s (Box 23, Folder 29)
    - Productive Forces (capitalist production possibilities, etc.), 1907-1946 (Box 23, Folder 30)
    - Purges - Old Bolsheviks decline, 1921, 1925 (Box 23, Folder 31)
    - Quotations and Clippings - Book reviews, ca.1920 (Box 23, Folder 32)
    - Excerpts from Foreign Affairs - Russia, Ireland, China, etc., 1922-1925 (Box 23, Folder 33)
    - "Right Opposition" and "Brandlerite Split", 1917-1930 (Box 23, Folder 34)
    - Second Socialist International, 1916 (Box 23, Folder 35)
    - Foreign Affairs - 2 articles on the 2nd International early 1900's, late1800s (Box 23, Folder 36)
    - 2 1/2 International - Hamburg Unity, Re-Unity of Pight and Center, 1920-1923 (Box 23, Folder 37)
    - Social-Democracy; points of argument - Russian Right Danger, 1918-1929, 1942 (Box 23, Folder 38)
    - Socialism in one country, 1921-1926 (Box 24, Folder 1)
    - Soviets (factory cells) - Sovietism, German Soviets, 1917-1930 (Box 24, Folder 2)
    - "Splits" - Radek on splitting during War, 1907-1919 (Box 24, Folder 3)
    - Stalin-Hitler Pact - "A Missing Page in Soviet Historiography: The Nazi-Soviet Partnership" by Vladimir Petrov, 1930s-1940s (Box 24, Folder 4)
    - Stalinism - ECCI - its powers over sections, "Democr. Dictatorship," Unknown Bolshevism, Political Prisoners, Stalin's death, Unity in Russian SD, 1901-1956 (Box 24, Folder 5)
    - Stalinism - (M.S. Polemic on Reform of'), undated (Box 24, Folder 6)
    - Stockholm Conference, 1917 (Box 24, Folder 7)
    - "3rd period mystery" - Kautsky on Dictatorship, Luxemburg and War, Lenin, Parliamentarism, Parity Committees", 1921-1930 (Box 24, Folder 8)
    - Third International (History of), undated (Box 24, Folder 9)
    - Tito - Stalinism and Socialism, Cominform, 1948-1961 (Box 24, Folder 10)
    - Trade Unions - after War, fractions, union before Russian Rev., undated (Box 24, Folder 11)
    - Trotsky - Stalin struggle - Stalin on industrialization, permanent Revolution, socialism, Lenin Testament, 1917-1936 (Box 24, Folder 12)
    - Study of Walter Ulbright by Carola Stern, 1930s-1940s (Box 24, Folder 13)
    - United Front - Russians and United Front, 1917-1933 (Box 24, Folder 14)
    - War Question (A) - War Conferences, 1893-1917 (Box 24, Folder 15)
    - War Question (B) - "Socialist Imperialism," Wartime "Bought" Revolutionists, Kautsky on War, 1904-1918 (Box 24, Folder 16)
    - War - Fascism, United Front (excerpts from newspapers), 1927-1935 (Box 24, Folder 17)
    - Beatrice Webb's Diaries - (extracts), 1918-1924 (Box 24, Folder 18)
    - Beatrice Webb and Mensheviks, 1925 (Box 24, Folder 19)
    - Eve of WWI - French militarism, Belgian Elections 1914, Legacy of lst Int'l, 1906-1914 (Box 24, Folder 20)
    - Revolutionary expectations after WWI: C.I. illusions, Zinoviev Big Talk, 1918-1920s (Box 24, Folder 21)
    - Post War Revolutionary Wave - "Revolutionary Epoch", Left Turn in TU's 1928, 1918-1928 (Box 24, Folder 22)
    - "Cold War" and Post WWII Relations (see also: China) - "Communism Today: A Refresher Cours7r, 1940s-1960s (Box 24, Folder 23)
    - WhrII - Stalinism and Post MN'II - Peace Treaties 1919, Pre 1939 Struggle Vs. Hitler, Post War Policy, Hitler, 1919-1949 (Box 24, Folder 24)
    - Zimerwald Conference - Basel, Bolsheviks and Zimmerwald; International conferences, 1915 (Box 24, Folder 25)
  - PART C: BY NAME OF AUTHOR (all articles reprinted from the American Slavic and East faropean Review except folder 29)
    - Plackstock., Paul W. - "The Occupation Fund Documents: A Reassessment of A Crude and Ignorant Forgery'," (Dec.1954), 1880s-1935 (Box 25, Folder 1)
    - Bradley, J.F.N. - "Czech Nationalism and Socialism in 1905", (Feb.1960) (Box 25, Folder 2)
    - Corbett, D.M. - The Rehabilitation of Mjykola Skrypnyk", (Jun.1963), 1917-1933 (Box 25, Folder 3)
    - Daniels, Robert V. - "The State and. Revolution: A Case Stutly in the Genesis and Transformation of Communist Ideology", (Jan.1953), 1917-1939 (Box 25, Folder 4)
    - Dziewanowski, M.K. -"WWI and the Marxist Movement of Poland," (Jan.1953), 1914-1918 (Box 25, Folder 5)
    - Dziewanowski, M.K. - "The Foundation of the C.P. of Poland", (Apr.1952), 1917-1920 (Box 25, Folder 6)
    - Dziewanowski, M.K. - "Social Democrats vs. Social Patriots: The Origins of the Split of the Marxist Movement in Poland", (Jan.1951), 1880s-1918 (Box 25, Folder 7)
    - Hodgson, John H. - "The Paasikivi Line", Apr.1959), 1918-1950s (Box 25, Folder 8)
    - Jelavich, Chas. and Barbara - "The Occupational Fund Democrats: Additional Evidence", (Oct.1955) (Box 25, Folder 9)
    - Maehl, Wm. - The Anti-Russian Tide in German Socialism, 1918-20", (Apr.1959), 1914-1933 (Box 25, Folder 10)
    - McNeal, Robert H. - "Lenin's Attack on Stalin: Review and Appraisal", (Oct.1959), 1904-1920s, 1956 (Box 25, Folder 11)
    - Page, Stanley W. - "Lenin, The National Question and the Baltic States, 1917-19", (Jan. 1948), 1917-1919 (Box 25, Folder 12)
    - Page, Stanley W. - "The Russian Proletariat ancl World Revolution: Lenin's views to 1914", (Jan.1951), 1849-1914 (Box 25, Folder 13)
    - Richards, Edward P. - "The Shaping of the Comintern", (Apr.1959), 1919-1928 (Box 25, Folder 14)
    - Rintala, Marvin - "The Problem of Generations in Finnish Communism", (Apr.1958), 1905-1950s (Box 25, Folder 15)
    - Rintala, Marvin - "Vaino Tanner in Finnish Politics," (Feb.1961), 1905-1950s (Box 25, Folder 16)
    - Skilling, H. Gordon - "The Comintern and Czechoslovakia", (Apr.1960), 1921-1929 (Box 25, Folder 17)
    - Skilling, 14. Gordon - "Gottwald and the Folshevization of the Communist Party of Czechoslovakia", (Dec.1961), 1929-1939 (Box 25, Folder 18)
    - Smith, C. Jay, Jr. - "Letter", (Dec.1960), 1918-1922 (Box 25, Folder 19)
    - Smith, C. Jay, Jr. - "Russia and the Origins of the Finnish Civil War of 1918", (Dec. 1955) 1905-18', 1898-1904, 1905-1918 (Box 25, Folder 20)
    - Snell, John L. - "The Russian Revolution and the German Social Democratic Party", (Oct.1956), 1914-1917 (Box 25, Folder 21)
    - Staar, Richard F. - "The Political Bureau of the United Polish Workers' Party", (Apr.1956), 1930s-1950s (Box 25, Folder 22)
    - Staar, Richard F. - "Third Congress of the Polish Communist Party", (Feb. 1960), 1940s-1960s (Box 25, Folder 23)
    - Szeftel, Marc. - "Facts of Russian History and its Philosophy as viewed by B.D. Wolfe..." (Jan.1956), 1901-1917 (Box 25, Folder 24)
    - Szeftel, Marc. - "Letter", (Oct.1956), 1907-1914 (Box 25, Folder 25)
    - Toma, Peter A. - "The Slovak Soviet Republic of 1919", (Apr.1958) (Box 25, Folder 26)
    - Vettes, Wm. - The 1903 Schism of the Bulgarian Social Democracy and the Second International", (Dec.1960) (Box 25, Folder 27)
    - Wolfe, Bertram D. - "In Defense of Three Who Made a Revolution", ca.Jan 1956 (Box 25, Folder 28)
    - Wicks, Harry - Research done for M.S. - British intervention in Georgia (USSR) - Kamenoff's visit to Britain - Hungarian Revolution in 1919 - Revolutionary Situation in Europe - 1919 - Revolutionary Trade Union of Britain - Anglo-Russian Trade Agreement - British Trade Union Delegation to Russia - Character of Red Army - 1919 post WWI Situation in Great Britain - German Rev. 1919, 1917-1930s (Box 25, Folder 29)
  - PART D: ALLEGED MATERIALS OF THE POLITBURO TPANSLATED AND EVALUATED BY LOVETNTHAL
    - Soviet Intelligence material from the German archives, 1930s (Box 26, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence: Shachtman-Loventhal, Loventhal-Wolfe, Fvaluation of Resolution by Orlov, 1934-193S (Box 26, Folder 2)
    - Chapter #13: The Comintern and the Politburo, 1919-1941 (Box 26, Folder 3)
    - The Resolution of the Politburo (CPSU, on Soviet Foreign Po licy, 1931-1936 (Box 26, Folder 4)
    - Politburo Resolutions on Foreign Policy: 1934 pp.1-339, Apr 1905 (Box 26, Folder 5)
    - Introduction to Politburo Resolutions pp.1-343 (carbon copy), undated (Box 26, Folder 6)
    - Introduction to Politburo Resolutions on Soviet Foreign Policy Appendices A-I, L-0, undated (Box 27, Folder 1)
    - NKID Correspondence-Introduction Documents pp.743-877, undated (Box 27, Folder 2)
    - Politburo Resolutions on Soviet Foreign Policy 1935, pp.340-742 (Box 27, Folder 3)
- Series III: Correspondence (microfilmed)
  - Part A: Individuals
    - Ahern, Marty (Workers Party), 1946 (Box 28, Folder 1)
    - Alba, Victor, 1957 (Box 28, Folder 2)
    - Alexander, Robert J. (Professor of comparative economics), 1953-1964 (Box 28, Folder 3)
    - Alexander's ms. of Intro to Latin Am. Trotskyism, 1969-1972 (Box 28, Folder 4)
    - Baird: Virginia and Michael (YSL), 1962 (Box 28, Folder 5)
    - Banerjee, Bimal (Indian Socialist, Trade Unionist), 1966 (Box 28, Folder 6)
      Microfilm Reel Number 34
    - Barton Tom (Member of YPSL), 1961 (Box 28, Folder 7)
    - Benson, H.W. ftion' Democracy in Action), 1947-1967 (Box 28, Folder 8)
    - Bonnet, Marguerite (France), 1962-1963 (Box 28, Folder 9)
    - Briggs, Win., 1957-1960 (Box 28, Folder 10)
    - Brogug, Pierre (Scholar,, France), 1972 (Box 28, Folder 11)
    - Brumberg, Abraham (Editor of Problems of Communism), 1964-1968 (Box 28, Folder 12)
    - Buhle,' Paul (Radical Educ. Project, Historian), 1966 (Box 28, Folder 13)
    - Bumett, James, 1957, 1964-1969 (Box 28, Folder 14)
    - Carthy, Albert (Socialist International, London), 1962 (Box 28, Folder 15)
    - Chauvin, Jean R. (French socialist), 1952-1953 (Box 28, Folder 16)
    - Cleland, Hugh (a.k.a. Gerry McDermott - ISL, SP), 1956-1962 (Box 28, Folder 17)
    - Cohen, Barney - Member of ISL?, SP, 1948-1961, 1961-1971 (Box 28, Folder 18-19)
    - Collinet, Simone and Michael (France), 1963 (Box 28, Folder 20)
    - Commentary, 1967 (Box 28, Folder 21)
    - Congress for Cultural Freedom (Irving Kristol) - Asia Tour, 1965-1966 (Box 28, Folder 22)
    - Conley, Tom, ca.1946-1956, 1956 (Box 28, Folder 23)
    - Cornell: Industrial and Labor Relations School (see also: Series IV, 39/11), 1964-1967 (Box 28, Folder 24)
    - Daniels, Robert V. (Prof. of history, re: Scandinavian resources), 1964-1965 (Box 28, Folder 25)
    - Davidson, Joe (S.P., Philadelphia), 1960-1964 (Box 28, Folder 26)
    - Decter, Moshe - Jewish Minorities Research, NYC, 1962 (Box 28, Folder 27)
    - Dewar, Hugo, 1951, 1962-1964 (Box 28, Folder 28)
    - Diamond, Joe - Denmark, 1962-1964 (Box 28, Folder 29)
    - Dissent, 1954-1970 (Box 28, Folder 30)
    - Dix, Bernard (British), 1925-1929 (Box 28, Folder 31)
      Microfilm Reel Number 35
    - Dobbs, Farrell, 1968 (Box 28, Folder 31A)
    - Draper, Hal (Workers Party), 1945-1947, 1960, 1964 (Box 28, Folder 32)
    - Draper, Theodore (Ted) (Historian of Am. Communism), 1953-1969 (Box 28, Folder 33)
    - Dunayevskaya, Raya (a.k.a. Freddie Forrest), undated (Box 28, Folder 34)
    - Dziewanowski, M.K. (Professor of history), 1968 (Box 28, Folder 35)
    - Eastman, Max (Ex-Trotskyist writer), 1962 (Box 28, Folder 36)
    - English, Maurice (Temple University Press), 1970 (Box 28, Folder 37)
    - Enright, Ted. (ISL), 1956-1957 (Box 28, Folder 38)
    - Farrell, James I. (author, former Trotskyist), 1946-1948 (Box 28, Folder 39)
    - Feldman, Paul (Editor of New America), 1965-1966 (Box 28, Folder 40)
    - Fenwick, James M. (Workers Party), 1946 (Box 28, Folder 41)
    - Feuer, Lewis S. (Professor, University of California) speaking engagement, 1960 (Box 28, Folder 42)
    - Fischer, Ruth -, 1947-1963 (Box 28, Folder 43)
    - Freymond, Jacques (Geneva), 1964 (Box 28, Folder 44)
    - Fromm, Erich (Author, SP) Socialist Forum, proposed journal, 1958-1959 (Box 28, Folder 45)
    - Frank, Pierre (Trotskyist) letter from Turkey., 1932 (Box 28, Folder 46)
    - Garber, Alex - (Boulder, SP, prof. of sociology) - Cuban question, speaking engagements: News Reports, 1960-1971, 1961 (Box 29, Folder 1-2)
    - Gaussman, Bill (SP) - attitudes toward MS's membership, British elections, 1964 (Box 29, Folder 3)
    - Geltman, Manny (Dissent editor), 1963 (Box 29, Folder 4)
    - Ghitelman, Steven----o-n-Bolshevism and Stalinism, 1972 (Box 29, Folder 5)
    - Gilbert, Rodney - on Socialist Labor Party and on Stalinism, 1949 (Box 29, Folder 6)
    - Glotzer, Al (Ex SWP, WP a.k.a. Gates), 1947, 1969 (Box 29, Folder 7)
    - Gnizi, Haim (Researcher) - on V.F. Calverton, 1967 (Box 29, Folder 8)
    - Goldman, Albert (Ex SWP, WP), 1940, 1946-1947 (Box 29, Folder 9)
    - Gotkowski) Luis (a.k.a. Rudzienski, A. - Journalist) - Poland CP, Israel, 1947-1970 (Box 29, Folder 10)
    - Gould, Nathan (Natie) - Workers Party, 1947-1948 (Box 29, Folder 11)
      Microfilm Reel Number 36 (Note: folders out of order on this reel)
    - Graham, Peter, 1961 (Box 29, Folder 12)
    - Greenwood, L.R. (Student of political science), 1959 (Box 29, Folder 13)
    - Griffith, William (Center for International Studies), 1964 (Box 29, Folder 14)
    - Grossman, Justin, 1951, 1962-1963 (Box 29, Folder 15)
    - Hallinan, Vincent, 1957 (Box 29, Folder 16)
    - Harrington, Mike (SP) - theory of decadence; European travels (see also: Box 18/14-20), undated (Box 29, Folder 17)
    - Haston, Jock and Millie (British socialists) - on International, 1949-1970 (Box 29, Folder 18)
    - Held, Walter (German Trotskyist), 1938 (Box 29, Folder 19)
    - Herreshoff, David (Socialist) - on regroupment, 1956 (Box 29, Folder 20)
    - Heumos, Herbert, 1952 (Box 29, Folder 20A)
    - Hill, Norman (SP/SDF executive secretary), 1961-1964 (Box 29, Folder 21)
    - Holubnychy, Vesvolod and Lydia - ("Felix") socialist scholar - Ukraine historical resources and others, 1962-1963 (Box 29, Folder 22)
    - Hoopes, Darlington (SP) - speaking engagement, 1960-1962 (Box 29, Folder 23)
    - Hoover Institution - Conference on 100 years of revolutionary internationals (see also: series IV Box 39/23 and Box 40/13), 1964-1966 (Box 29, Folder 24)
    - Horowitz Rachelle (see also: Box 18), 1963, 1970 (Box 29, Folder 25)
    - Howe, Irving (Editor Trotsky anthology (draft of introduction), 1948-1963 (Box 29, Folder 26)
    - Howe, Irving (Editor) - on Socialist Party and Vietnam, 1963-1971 (Box 29, Folder 27)
    - Hudson, Michael (Publisher), 1961 (Box 29, Folder 28)
    - Issacs, Harold R. (Writer) - China historical resources, 1970 (Box 29, Folder 29)
    - Jacobs, Sara (Companion to Natalia Trotsky) - Trotsky's literary rights, 1958-1963 (Box 29, Folder 30)
    - Jewsish Labor Bund, 1966-1967 (Box 29, Folder 31)
    - Jacobson, Julius and Phyllis (Editor, New Politics), 1960-1963 (Box 29, Folder 32)
    - Johnpoll, Bernard K. (SP, professor at SUNY-Albany), 1967-1968 (Box 29, Folder 33)
    - Kahn, Thomas (L.I.D.), 1971 (Box 29, Folder 34)
      Microfilm Reel Number 37
    - Kelman, Steve (YPSL, Harvard Chapter), 1967 (Box 29, Folder 35)
    - Kendall, Walter (British socialist), 1963-1964 (Box 29, Folder 36)
    - Kerry, Karolyn (SWP editor) - historical resources, 1969 (Box 29, Folder 37)
    - Kohak, Erazim V. (SP, Boston), 1971 (Box 29, Folder 38)
    - Labedz, Leopold (British socialist, editor), 1964-1970 (Box 29, Folder 39)
    - Lazitch, Branko (Socialist scholar, Yugoslav?), 1964, 1970 (Box 29, Folder 40)
    - Lens, Sidney (Socialist) - regroupment, 1957, 1963 (Box 29, Folder 41)
    - Leonetti, Alfonso (Italian socialist), 1970 (Box 29, Folder 42)
    - Leopold, Louis (Leo) (SP) - unity talks, 1955, 1971-1972 (Box 29, Folder 43)
    - Lerner, Shirley (Am. ISLer in England), 1953-1955 (Box 29, Folder 44)
    - Levine, Issac Don (Author) Mind of an Assassin (re: Trotsky's assassination), 1956-1968 (Box 29, Folder 45)
    - Lewytzkyj, Boris (German socialist) - historical resources, 1949-1968 (Box 29, Folder 46)
    - Loeb., John (Socialist journalist) - Boston socialists, 1954-1956 (Box 30, Folder 1)
    - Lofman, Jake (Socialist) - Poland historical resources, ca.1964 (Box 30, Folder 2)
    - Loventhal, Milton (Author) - Politburo resolutions (see also: Box 26), 1966 (Box 30, Folder 3)
    - McAvoy, Clifford and Muriel (Socialist Labor leader), 1957 (Box 30, Folder 4)
    - McBride, John (Worker, member of ISL), 1956 (Box 30, Folder 5)
    - MacDonald, Dwight and Nancy, undated (Box 30, Folder 5A)
    - MacFadyen, Gavin (British socialist), 1962-1963 (Box 30, Folder 6)
    - McKinney, E.R. (Dave) (Workers Party) - organizational difficulties, 1948-1969 (Box 30, Folder 7)
    - McReynolds, David (SP) - regroupment, Vietnam War, 1956-1966 (Box 30, Folder 8)
    - Malamuth, Charles (Scholar of Communist movement), 1962 (Box 30, Folder 9)
    - Mankind (India) (socialist monthly), 1955-1960 (Box 30, Folder 10)
    - Mannheim, Mary and Frank (Writers), 1961-1963 (Box 30, Folder 11)
    - Marquart, Frank (SP) - questions on Leninism, 1957 (Box 30, Folder 12)
    - Martinson, testing debate, Trotsky in Mexico, etc., 1951-1963, 1972 (Box 30, Folder 13)
    - Matthofer, Hans (German socialist), 1962-1963 (Box 30, Folder 14)
    - Meijer, J.M. - Slavic studies (Amsterdam), 1963 (Box 30, Folder 15)
    - Mendelson, Saul (WP), 1949 (Box 30, Folder 16)
    - Milgrim, Morris, 1961 (Box 30, Folder 17)
    - Miller, Bruce (SP attorney) - SP convention, speaking engagement, 1959-1963 (Box 30, Folder 18)
    - Mirmak, Lillian (SP Philadelphia), 1961 (Box 30, Folder 19)
    - Letter to Yetta (Barsh) from George (Mohr), undated (Box 30, Folder 19A)
    - Mrvichin, Diane (YPSL/SP Sacramento) - speaking engagements, 1966-1972 (Box 30, Folder 20)
    - Munis,' G. - (Pseud. for Manuel Fernandes Grandizo, Mexican Socialist), 1947, 1950 (Box 30, Folder 21)
      Microfilm Reel Number 38
    - Murphy, John (ex-SWP), 1954-1955 (Box 30, Folder 22)
    - Muste, A.J. (Socialist leader, Fellowship of Reconciliation) American Forum (see also: Box 3S/22-24), 1956-1958 (Box 30, Folder 23)
    - Naville, Pierre (French Socialist), 1963 (Box 30, Folder 24)
    - Neurath, Alois (German Socialist), 1952-1953 (Box 30, Folder 25)
    - New International correspondence - on Leninism, 1951-1958 (Box 30, Folder 26)
    - New York Times letter to editor on defense of Trotskyists, 1947 (Box 30, Folder 27)
    - Newman, Robert P. (Prof. at U. of Pittsburgh) - speaking, 1968 (Box 30, Folder 28)
    - Nikolaevsky, Boris (Scholar), 1964 (Box 30, Folder 29)
    - Nomad, Max, 1963 (Box 30, Folder 30)
    - Noskin, Bernard (Atty) - passport case victory, 1955 (Box 30, Folder 31)
    - Novack, George (SWP, writer) - Trotsky's writings, 1962-1963 (Box 30, Folder 32)
    - Pablo' (French Socialist) - Trotsky archives (see also: Box 30/41), undated (Box 30, Folder 33)
    - Papcun,George J. (SP, Tucson), 1960 (Box 30, Folder 34)
    - Parisot, Paul, 1948 (Box 30, Folder 35)
    - Paskal, Oscar (ISQ - MS on sound equipment, 1956-1967 (Box 30, Folder 36)
    - Peret Benjamin (French Socialist in Mexico), 1947 (Box 30, Folder 37)
    - Pettinato, Vincent (Former ISQ, 1963 (Box 30, Folder 38)
    - Plastrick, Stanley (Nephew? Overseas), 1945 (Box 30, Folder 39)
    - Raol T.R. (Indian Socialist) - Modern India Publications, 1952-1954 (Box 30, Folder 40)
    - Raptis, Michel (aka Pablo, Greek Trotskyist-leader of F.I. until 1960s), Oct 6, 1947 (Box 30, Folder 41)
    - Rawick, George (SP) historical resources, 1960 (Box 30, Folder 42)
    - Rebha, Herman CWP unionist, Germany), 1952, 1967, 1972 (Box 30, Folder 43)
    - Rigby, T.H. (Australian Socialist), 1966 (Box 30, Folder 44)
    - Rizzi' Bruno (Italian Socialist author) - includes pamphlet, 1965 (Box 30, Folder 45)
    - Robbins, Jack Alan (Fordham University) - US Trotskyists bibliography, 1928-1941 (Box 30, Folder 46)
    - Roche, John P. (former SPer; ADA), 1963 (Box 30, Folder 47)
    - Rosdolsky, Roman (Socialist historian)(see also: Box 38/23), 1949-1950 (Box 30, Folder 48)
    - Rosenthal, Gerard (French Socialist) --Trotsky archives, 1948-1955 (Box 30, Folder 49)
    - Rosmer, Alfred - (Griot, French Trotskyist) - Trotsky's literary estate; debates, 1949-1963 (Box 30, Folder 50-51)
    - Sacks, Milton I. (Brandeis U., SP) - SP exchange with S. Vietnam, 1962, 1971 (Box 30, Folder 52)
    - Scharf, Jeronima. and Jacques (French Socialists), 1965 (Box 30, Folder 53)
    - Schelley, Dan and Sara CISL, SP) - SP debate on Vietnam, 1956-1970 (Box 30, Folder 54)
    - Sedov, Leon (Trotsky's son), 1936 (Box 31, Folder 1)
      Microfilm Reel Number 39
    - Sedova-Trotsky, Natalia (Widow of Trotsky) - break with 4th International and SWP, 1947-1951 (Box 31, Folder 2)
    - Sedova-Trotsky, Natalia, 1952-1960 (Box 31, Folder 3-5)
    - Sedova-Trotsky - financial correspondence, 1956-1959 (Box 31, Folder 6)
    - Sedova-Trotsky, Natalia - Including her death in 1962, 1945-1963 (Box 31, Folder 7)
    - Sedova-Trotsky, Natalia - Shachtman's agreements re: Trotsky's literary estate, undated (Box 31, Folder 8)
    - Serge, Victor (Author on Trotsky) - biographical note, 1947 (Box 31, Folder 9)
    - Sexton., Patricia (Writer), 1968 (Box 31, Folder 10)
    - Shain, Charles (YPSL,, East Bay Organizer) - disputes; speaking, 1961 (Box 31, Folder 11)
    - Silone, Ignazio (Italian Socialist), 1969-1970 (Box 31, Folder 12)
    - Sinclair, Louis (Scottish scholar) - Trotsky historiography, 1962 (Box 31, Folder 13)
    - Singer, Rube (SP) - speaking, 1961 (Box 31, Folder 14)
    - Slaiman, Don (Am. ISLer in England), 1953-1957 (Box 31, Folder 15)
    - Slavin, Morris (professor, socialist), 1963-1964 (Box 31, Folder 16)
    - Smith, Kenneth J. (leader, Philadelphia Ethical Society) - speaking, 1961-1964 (Box 31, Folder 17)
    - Smith, Larry G. (Socialist a.k.a. O'Conner) - Arab socialists, 1947-1954 (Box 31, Folder 18)
    - Socialist Party - Personal correspondence with members, undated (Box 31, Folder 19)
    - Souvarine, Boris (Editor of le Contrat Social), 1962-1964 (Box 31, Folder 20)
    - Stack, Mel (SP), 1960 (Box 31, Folder 21)
    - Stamm, Thomas (WP), 1946-1947 (Box 31, Folder 22)
    - Stein, Fred (Photographer) - historical sources, 1967 (Box 31, Folder 23)
      Microfilm Reel Number 40
    - Stein, Mordechai (Israeli socialist), 1961 (Box 31, Folder 24)
    - Stern Carola (German publisher), undated (Box 31, Folder 25)